And welcome to day five.
5일째에 오신 걸 환영해요
For reals.
진짜로요
We're actually in the proper Jupyter notebook.
주피터 공책에 있는 거예요
This time we're in day five, in week five, ready for action.
오늘은 5일째예요 5주 차죠, 준비됐어요
And it's the same as before.
예전과 똑같아요
It's a duplicate of day four, not day four and a half.
4일 반이 아니라 4일 차와 똑같은 거예요
We're using the Chroma Datastore here, and I'm going to really quickly go through this because you
크로마 Datastore를 사용하고 있습니다 빠르게 살펴보겠습니다 이미
know all of this already.
다 알고 계시니까요
And we're going to get back to our Gradio interface.
그리고 그래디오 인터페이스로 돌아갈 거예요 get it
Just like that.
이렇게요
It caught up with us.
그게 우리를 따라잡았죠
It's drawn.
그려진 거예요
It's 2D and 3D diagrams behind the scenes.
무대 뒤에서 2D와 3D 도표가 펼쳐지죠
But no time for that.
하지만 그럴 시간이 없어요
Now.
지금요
We need to press on.
계속 가야 해요
Uh, first of all, I might as well show you that that aviary test we did before still works in chroma
먼저 보여드릴 게 있어요 전에 했던 조류 실험은 바이브스 실험처럼 채도로도
as it did in vice.
효과가 있어요
So let's just quickly try that ourselves.
우리도 빨리 해보죠
Um, what did aviary spelt wrong do before ensure?
철자를 틀리게 쓴 새장은 어떤 역할을 했죠?
Um, and I imagine.
상상이 돼요
We'll see.
두고 봐야죠
Yes.
네
That chroma has no problems whatsoever with that either.
채도가 전혀 문제가 없어요
No surprises there.
놀랍지도 않네요
Okay, but let me now show you something which isn't going to go so well.
좋아요, 하지만 잘 안 될 만한 걸 보여드리죠
First of all, I want to take a peek at an employee HR document.
먼저 직원 인사 자료를 좀 볼게요
If we go into our knowledge base and we go to employees, we're going to look at the employee record
지식 기반으로 가서 직원들을 살펴보죠 맥신 톰프슨의
for a certain Maxine Thompson.
직원 기록을 살펴볼 거예요
Let's open this with markdown.
마크다운으로 시작하죠
So we see it in its full markdown glory.
그래서 완전히 파손된 모습을 보게 되죠
Here is HR record for Maxine Thompson, um, a data engineer in Austin, Texas.
맥신 톰프슨의 인사 기록이에요 텍사스주 오스틴에 사는 데이터 엔지니어죠
And the thing I wanted to draw your attention to for one second is that if you look down here, you'll
잠시 주목해 주셨으면 하는 게 있어요 여기 아래를 보시면
notice that Maxine was recognized as the Ensure Elm Innovator of the year in 2023.
맥신이 2023년 올해의 엘름 이노베이터로 선정된 게 보일 거예요
She received the prestigious I o T Award in Elm Innovator of the year award in 2023.
2023년 엘름 최고의 혁신가 부문에서 아이오티상을 수상했죠
Now, I have to confess, I added this sentence in myself.
고백하자면 이 문장은 제가 추가했어요
It wasn't as if this was, uh, invented as part of the synthetic data, uh, by, uh, GPT four or
GPT 4나 클로드가 만든 합성 데이터의 일부로 만들어진 건 아니었어요
This is all my doing.
다 내 탓이에요
And it's awful.
끔찍해요
So blame me.
그러니 날 탓해요
Uh, so what we're going to do now is we're going to go back to our day five, and we are going to ask
이제 5일 차로 돌아가서 질문을 하나 할게요 누가 이겼을까요?
Oh, we say, who received the prestigious, uh and Shriram Innovator of the year award in 2023.
누가 2023년에 권위 있는 슈리람 올해의 혁신자 상을 받았는지를요
And let's see what it says.
뭐라고 쓰여 있는지 보죠
It says I don't know.
모른다고 나오네요
And quite a blunt way.
직설적으로 말하네요
Quite curt.
퉁명스럽죠
Uh, so that's interesting.
그게 흥미로워요
Uh, it has failed.
실패하고 말았죠
That was information that it was provided.
그게 우리가 제공한 정보였어요
It was there in the documents.
서류에 다 나와 있었어요
And that is a bit disappointing.
비트가 좀 실망스럽네요
And so the thing to do now is to try and diagnose this problem.
그러니 이제 이 문제를 진단해 봐야죠
And in doing so, we're going to learn a little bit about how Lang Chain works under the hood.
그렇게 함으로써 랑체인의 작동 원리를 비트 아래서 배울 거예요
And it's not going to be very surprising.
그리 놀랍지도 않을 거예요
Uh, so here we get to see what's going on.
여기선 어떤 상황인지 볼 수 있죠 Get up
Uh, there is this very useful thing we can do, which is create something called the standard out callback
아주 유용한 게 있어요 표준 아웃 콜백 처리기라는 걸 만드는 거죠
handler, which, much as it sounds, is going to be something which will let us print to the standard
말 그대로 뒤에서 무슨 일이 일어나는지 표준에 프린트할
out what is going on behind the scenes.
수 있게 해주는 거예요
So this is the same familiar code that you're very used to.
여러분이 아주 익숙한 동일한 코드예요
We create the alarm.
경보를 울리는 거죠
We create the memory.
메모리를 만드는 거죠
We create the retriever and we create our conversation chain in this beautiful one liner passing in
리트리버와 대화 사슬을 만듭니다 이 아름다운 한 줄이 LM을 통과하죠
the LM, the retriever, the memory.
리트리버, 메모리요
And now you can see I'm passing in one more thing, which is a list of callbacks.
제가 하나를 더 넘기고 있는 게 보이시죠 콜백 목록이에요
And I'm only creating one callback in here, which is this standard out callback handler.
여기선 한 개의 콜백만 만들고 있어요 표준 아웃 콜백 처리기죠
And that as you can probably, uh, expect, is going to be printing, uh, repeatedly to standard out
여러분이 예상하시듯이 반복적으로 표준에 프린트될 겁니다 이 대화
as this conversation chain runs.
사슬이 실행될 때요
So here is the question again who won?
다시 문제입니다 누가 이겼을까요?
I put it differently.
전 다르게 표현했어요 Put it up Put it up Put it up
Let's do it the same way.
똑같이 해 보죠
Who received the prestigious Iet Award in 2023?
2023년 Iet상을 받은 사람은 누구일까요?
There we go.
됐어요
We'll ask that question.
그 질문을 해보죠
We'll get back the answer.
Get get get, get get, get 답을 찾아볼게요
We'll see what it says.
뭐라고 쓰여 있는지 보죠
So we get this kind of trace as we look through it, which gives us a bit of insight into how Lang Chain
비트 박스를 통해 흔적을 얻으면 랭 체인이 어떻게 돌아가는지 알
works.
수 있죠
It has these different objects.
다양한 물체가 있어요
These are called the chain that are sort of hooked together as it goes through the steps of building
이런 걸 체인이라고 하는데 대화를 구성하는 단계를 거치면서 연결되는
the conversation, the Rag query.
거예요 래그 쿼리요
And you can actually use different callbacks to be printing lots more detail about what's happening
다양한 콜백을 이용해 각 단계에서 일어나는 일에 대해 보다 상세히
at each stage, should you wish.
프린트할 수도 있어요 원한다면요
But what we really care about is the prompt that ends up going to GPT four.
하지만 정말 중요한 건 GPT 4에 도달하는 프롬프트죠
And here it is.
여기 있네요
System.
시스템요
Use the following piece of context to answer the user's question.
다음 컨텍스트를 이용해 사용자의 질문에 답하세요
If you don't know the answer, just say that you don't know.
모르면 모른다고 하면 되잖아요
Don't try to make up an answer.
없는 말 지어내지 마세요
I think this is really interesting, because this is the prompt that specialists at Lang Chain, like
정말 흥미로운 건 랭 체인 전문가들이 다양한 llm에
experts, have crafted as an ideal prompt to send to different llms.
보낼 이상적인 프롬프트란 거예요
And so this is a great one for for you to steal and use in your own projects.
따라서 이건 여러분이 자신의 프로젝트에 사용하기에 아주 좋아요
It's very carefully written.
아주 공들여 쓴 거예요
It's clearly very effective because it stopped, uh, GPT four from hallucinating.
아주 효과적인 약이에요 GPT 4가 환각 증상을 보이지 않게 막았으니까요
Um, and so it's nice well worded prompting.
각본이 잘 짜여진 게 좋았어요
But here's the problem.
하지만 문제가 있어요
This is the context that was then provided to the to the LM coming up right here.
이 컨텍스트가 제공된 곳은∙∙∙ 여기 나오는 LM이죠
And you'll see that it is, in fact a few chunks taken from different chunks that we've got.
보시면 아시겠지만 여러 덩어리에서 몇 개만 추출한 거예요
It's 2 or 3 chunks and they appear to be taken from HR records.
두세 덩어리인데 인사 기록에서 빼낸 것 같아요
But they're not right.
하지만 옳지 않아요
Because they don't mention the I o t award.
아이오티상은 언급하지 않으니까요
So it's wrong chunks that have been identified unfortunately in this case.
안타깝게도 이 경우엔 엉뚱한 덩어리를 식별했어요
Um oh, and that this at the end here is is the question.
그리고 이 마지막 부분이 질문이에요
It says human who received the prestigious I o t award.
아이오티상을 받은 인간이라고 쓰여 있어요
I'm the human.
내가 인간이에요
Uh, and clearly there wasn't good context to answer that question in what comes above.
그 질문에 대한 답을 하기에는 좋은 맥락이 없었어요
And that's why the response was, I don't know.
그래서 이런 반응을 보였겠죠
So what can we do about this?
그럼 어떻게 해야 할까요?
Well, it's a it's a very common problem with Rag when you find that you're not providing the right
래그와 관련해 아주 흔한 문제입니다 올바른 컨텍스트를 제공하지 않을
context.
때요
And there's a few different things that you can do.
할 수 있는 게 몇 가지 있어요
Uh, one of them is to go back and look at your chunking strategy.
하나는 청킹 전략을 다시 살펴보는 거예요
How are you dividing documents into chunks?
서류를 어떻게 덩어리로 나누죠?
And are you doing that?
그러고 있어요?
Right.
네
And there's a few things that we could try right off the bat.
바로 시도해 볼 만한 게 몇 가지 있어요
One of them is instead of chunking, we could send entire documents in as the context.
그 중 하나는 청크링 대신에 전체 문서를 컨텍스트로 보낼 수 있다는 거죠
So we we just put full documents in Cromer and then we look for the document that's closest.
그래서 전체 문서를 get get get에 넣고 가장 가까운 문서를 찾아봤어요
We could also go the other way and chunk more, have more fine grained chunks, smaller chunks.
반대로 큼직큼직하게 잘라 입자가 곱거나 작을 수도 있어요
We can also investigate that overlap between chunks to see if we increase or decrease the overlap,
또한 덩어리 간의 중첩을 조사해서 겹치는 부분이 늘어나는지 줄어들는지 확인할
presumably increase.
수도 있죠
In this case, we are more likely to provide a useful chunk.
이런 경우에는 유용한 정보를 제공할 가능성이 더 크죠
So those are all things to investigate to get your chunking strategy working well so the right context
모두 조사해볼 만한 것들이에요. 청킹 전략이 잘 작동하도록 하기 위해서요. 그래서 올바른 컨텍스트가 제공되고 있어요.
is being provided.
Get up!
There is another thing.
한 가지 더 있어요
And it's very simple.
아주 간단해요
And it's what we're going to do in this case.
이 경우에 그렇게 할 거예요
And that is to control the number of chunks, the amount of context that actually does get sent in.
get의 개수를 조절하는 거죠 실제로 전송되는 컨텍스트의 양을요
Um, so in our case, we're just sending a I think it's actually three chunks that are getting sent
음, 저희 경우엔 그냥∙∙∙ 여기로 전송되는 건 3개일
in here, and you can actually control the number of chunks that get sent in, and you can do that in
거예요 전송되는 덩어리의 수를 컨트롤할 수 있어요 이렇게 할 수 있죠
When we create the retriever vector store as retriever, we can actually say how many chunks we want
리트리버 벡터 스토어를 리트리버로 생성할 때 얼마나 많은 덩어리를 반환하고 넘길지
returned and passed in.
정할 수 있어요
And in this case, I have specified now that I want 25 chunks to be created and passed in.
이 경우에 전 25개의 덩어리가 생성돼 전달되도록 지정했어요
As a general rule of thumb, it's a good idea to send a lot of context to the LLM.
경험상 LLM에 많은 컨텍스트를 보내는 게 좋아요
Llms are very good at, at uh, only focusing on relevant contexts and ignoring irrelevant context.
Rms는 관련 맥락에만 초점을 맞추고 불필요한 맥락을 무시하는 데 뛰어나요
So it's good practice to send plenty of chunks.
그러니 덩어리를 많이 보내는 게 좋아요
There are a few occasional situations where it's better not to do that.
그러지 않는 게 나은 상황도 가끔 있어요
One of them, for example, is in one of the very latest models that OpenAI is offering, a model which
예를 들어 오픈AI가 제공하는 최신 모델 중 하나가 그 예입니다 즉각적으로
looks in much more detail at the prompt and does some more analysis behind the scenes to really understand
더 자세히 살펴보고 보이지 않는 곳에서 분석을 통해 제대로 이해하는 모델이죠
it.
일종의 사고의 연속이죠
Um, and the recommendation there is that you don't provide lots of extra irrelevant context because
그리고 비관련 컨텍스트를 많이 제공하지 않는 걸 추천합니다 그러면 속도가
that will slow down and distract the model.
느려지고 모델이 산만해지니까요
But with those occasional examples to one side, general rule of thumb is that more context is generally
하지만 가끔씩 나오는 예들을 보면 경험상 일반적인 규칙은 더 많은 컨텍스트가
a good thing.
좋다는 거죠
And so in this case, there's not much harm in providing the 25 nearest chunks rather than 2 or 3 nearest
이 경우에는 큰 해가 되지 않아요 가장 가까운 25개를 두세 개보다 더 많이 주는
chunks.
거죠
We've got a total of what, 123 chunks.
덩어리가 총 123개예요
So this is still about a fifth of our total data.
그러니 이건 전체 데이터의 5분의 1에 불과해요
So we're not shipping our entire data set.
전체 데이터 세트를 보내는 게 아니에요
We're picking the most relevant 25 chunks, the most relevant fifth of our content to send the LLM.
가장 관련 있는 25개의 청크를 선택하고 있어요 LLM을 보내기 위한 콘텐츠 중 가장 관련 있는 5분의 1이죠
So let's see if this works.
잘 되는지 보죠
So we will run this.
이걸 실행할게요
And then as as before we will bring up our usual Gradio interface.
그리고 전처럼 평소대로 그래디오 인터페이스를 켜죠
And right off the bat we'll ask the question who won the uh sorry who received to use the.
그럼 바로 질문을 시작하죠 누가 이겼는지 누가 그걸 사용하게 됐는지요
So I keep it consistent.
그래서 일관성을 유지하죠
Who received the prestigious I t y Award in 2023.
2023년 아이티유상을 수상했죠
And let's see.
어디 보죠
Drum roll please.
드럼 부탁해요
Maxine.
맥신이에요
Maxine received the prestigious I o t 2023 award.
맥신은 명망 높은 Iot 2023 상을 받았어요
So indeed, providing more chunks to the LM did solve the problem.
달 착륙선에 더 많은 덩어리를 제공한 게 문제 해결이었죠
So with that, the exercise for you is to now go back, experiment with this.
이제 돌아가서 이걸 실험해 보세요
Try some hard questions.
어려운 질문을 해보세요
You could always insert a few things in the documents yourself and see what happens.
언제든 문서에 몇 가지 삽입해 어떻게 되는지 볼 수 있어요
Um, and then experiment with different chunking strategies.
그리고 다양한 청량 전략을 실험해 보는 거죠
Try full documents, try smaller chunks, maybe 100 characters with more and less overlap, and get
전체 문서를 입력해보세요 더 작은 덩어리로요 100글자 정도로요 더 많거나 덜 겹치게요 그게
a good feel for how that affects the quality of results and and how you can either give too little context.
결과의 질에 어떤 영향을 미치는지 느껴보세요 너무 적은 컨텍스트를 제공할 수도 있고요 Get it
Maybe you can see some effects of providing too much context.
너무 많은 컨텍스트를 제공하면 어떤 영향을 미치는지 알 수 있죠
Maybe that causes the responses to be less accurate.
그래서 NTSB의 반응이 less로 나오는 것 같아요
So experiment, get a good sense for the the the good and the bad, and a good knack for how to do this
그래서 좋은 점과 나쁜 점을 파악하고 가장 효과적인 방법을 잘 파악할 수 있도록요
in a way that is most effective.
get it
And I will see you for the next video to wrap up.
그럼 다음 영상에서 다시 만나요